P.D. Browne papers, Inclusive: 1860-1986, Bulk: 1950-1986
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
P.D. Browne papers
Inclusive: 1860-1986, Bulk: 1950-1986
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
347
Browne, P. D.
12 document boxes.
The P.D. Browne papers consist of materials reflecting Browne's work for Baylor University, his involvement with Seventh and James Baptist Church, and his research interests in Freestone County, Texas.
Administrative Information
Biography/Profile
Philip Dale Browne, or P.D. Browne, longtime educator in Central Texas, taught and supervised schools in Teague, Crystal City, Fairfield, and Baylor University. His other interests included American Civil War history, and he wrote extensively on several units from Freestone County. Much of his work on local Civil War history helped to preserve information that might otherwise have been lost through time.
Though he was named Philip Dale Browne, Philip preferred P.D. Browne as his name in everyday usage and formal writings, such as essays. His Texas educational career began in 1921-1922 as the principal of Teague High School in Freestone County. As of 1930, Browne was thirty years old, married, had one daughter, and lived in Freestone County. Through 1943 P.D. Browne taught and administered high schools in Crystal City and Fairfield, as well as attending the University of Texas for a year. In 1943-1944 Browne was a mathematics teacher at Baylor, but left to accept a position as education director and financial officer at 7th and James Baptist Church in Waco. After seven years teaching Bible classes and overseeing the monetary affairs of the church, Browne moved back to Baylor and taught mathematics and religion for the next twenty years. Upon his retirement in 1971, Browne accepted the directorship of the Baylor Retired Professor’s program for another nine years. Browne finally retired for good in 1982 after over fifty years of educational service to Central Texas.
In addition to his interests in mathematics and religion, Browne was also interested in local history. For a brief time Browne was the president of the Baylor Historical Society, but preferred the roles scholar and researcher. He was quite interested in the American Civil War, and especially in Confederate units from Central Texas. Though he wrote on broad Civil War topics such as Walker's Division, most of his writing emphasized the role of units, leaders, and events to do with Freestone County, Texas. One of his most important essays, “Captain T.D. Nettles and the Valverde Battery,” was the most accurate and inclusive essay on the Val Verde Battery to that point. Browne’s correspondence with Val Verde Battery commander T.D. Nettles’ son is preserved in the collection. Other essays were on L.D. Bradley’s Civil War company, W.L. Moody’s company, and A.M. Maddux’s company. Copies of these essays, including research notes, copies of muster rolls, and supporting secondary materials, can be found in this collection.
P.D. Browne made lasting contributions to education at Baylor University and various high schools throughout Central Texas, but his most important academic achievement was his work on obscure local Civil War military units at a time no one was doing research on them.
Scope and Content
The P.D. Browne papers begin with copies of 1860 documents and end in 1986. There are many essays about people and events in Freestone County, Texas, but the most historically valuable may be Browne's recollections and research about the post-war Confederate reunions held in Freestone County. Other essays describe various Confederate military units from Freestone County. Also included is Browne's personal correspondence and work-related productions from his faculty position at Baylor University.
Arrangement
The P.D. Browne papers were organized prior to this finding aid, with folder titles of varying usefulness and little organization in various places. An inventory was available.
Currently, the P.D. Browne papers are arranged in three series, I. Personal Papers, II. Baylor Materials, and III. Research Materials.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 347. Acquired 1976-08-02
Related Resources
Related references
Browne, Philip Dale. "Graves, Henry Lee." Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2013 October 4.
Confederate Reunion Grounds State Historic Site. "Buried Dreams: The Journey of the Old Val Verde Cannon." Accessed 2013 October 4.
Fitzhugh, Lester Newton. "Walker's Texas Division." Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2013 October 4.
Frazier, Donald S. “Val Verde Battery.” Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2011 December 16.
Hesler, Samuel B. "Pilgrim, Thomas J." Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2013 October 4.
Leffler, John. "Freestone County." Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2013 October 4.
Miller, Aragorn Storm. "Bradley, L. D." Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2013 October 4.
Shields, Douglas R. "Fairfield Female College." Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2013 October 7.
U.S. Bureau of the Census. 1930 United States Census, s.v. "Philip D. Browne." Freestone County, Texas. HeritageQuest Online, Accessed 2013 October 10.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- History.; Seventh and James Baptist Church (Waco, TX.)
Places
Confederate States of America -- History -- Societies, etc.; Texas -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Societies, etc.; Texas -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.
Subjects
Freestone County -- History.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Essays.; Financial records.; Photographs.; Programs.; Research notes.
- Personal Materials, circa 1918-1986, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  - Correspondence, 1919-1986, undated; 1
    Biography/Profile
    This subseries contains letters to and from P.D. Browne on a variety of topics. Most of the correspondence is personal, but there are some business and other letters present as well.
    - General, 1928-1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - General, 1934-1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - General, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - General, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - General, 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - General, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - General, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - General, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - General, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - General, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - General, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - General, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - General, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - General, 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - General, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - General, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - General, 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - General, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - General, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - General, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - General, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - General, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - General, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - General, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - General, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - General, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - General, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - General, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - General: (1 of 2), 1978 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - General: (2 of 2), 1978 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - General, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - General, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - General, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - General, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - General, 1984-1985, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Organizations, 1933-1936 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Organizations, 1937-1938 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Organizations, 1941-1984, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - P.D. Browne Military Service, 1919-1939 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Students in Military, 1941-1942 October (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Students in Military, 1942 November-1943 January (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Students in Military, 1943 February (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Students in Military, 1943 March-November (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Students in Military, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Students in Military, 1945 January-April (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Students in Military, 1945-1947 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Students in Military, 1952-1966 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Students in Military, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Speaking Engagements, 1932-1938 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Speaking Engagements, 1940-1943 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Speaking Engagements, 1944-1952 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Speaking Engagements, 1953-1958 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Speaking Engagements, 1959-1972 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Speaking Engagements, 1975-1983, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Schools, 1924-1929 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Schools, 1931-1932 October (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Schools, 1932 November-1934 February (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Schools, 1934 May-1934 October 22 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Schools, 1934 October 23-November 12 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Schools, 1934 November 13-1935 March (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Schools, 1935 August-1936 March (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Schools, 1936 April-August (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Schools, 1937-1938 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Schools, 1939-1940 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Schools, 1941 January-April (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Schools, 1941 October-1942 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Schools, 1943-1964 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Government Officials and Agencies, 1931-1939 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Government Officials and Agencies, 1941-1951 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Government Officials and Agencies, 1953-1970 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Government Officials and Agencies, 1972-1980, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Donations: (1 of 2), 1979-1984 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Donations: (2 of 2), 1979-1984 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Donations, 1985-1986, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Church, 1932-1942 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Church, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Church, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Church, 1946-1947 July (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Church, 1947 August-1949 August (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Church, 1949 September-1950 July (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Church, 1950 August-1951 July (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Church, 1951 August-October (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Church, 1951 November-1953 June (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Church, 1953 September-1955 February (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Church, 1955 May-1956 April (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Church, 1956 June-1957 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Church, 1958-1960 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Church, 1961-1963 October (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Church, 1963 November-1970 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Church, 1972-1974, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Baylor University Historical Society, 1946-1947, 1971-1972, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Financial, 1917-1941 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Financial, 1943-1972 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Legal Documents, 1921-1978; 2
    This subseries contains legal documents relating to P.D. Browne.
    - Contracts and Agreements, 1932-1939 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Charter of First Baptist Church, Fairfield, Texas, 1922 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - McLennan County Elections, 1968-1978 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Birth Certificates and Announcements, 1935-1942 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Teacher's Contracts, 1921-1940 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Financial Documents, 1921-1942; 3
    This subseries contains1 folder of various bills and receipts from P.D. Browne.
    - Bills and Receipts, 1921-1942 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Literary Productions, circa 1918-1986; 4
    This subseries contains various works written by or about P.D. Browne about various interests of his, including: Christian faith and learning, Baylor teaching materials, organizational minutes and event programs, and other topics.
    - General, circa 1918-1974 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - P.D. Browne Biographical Information, 1975-1986 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - "Study of Baylor University Students'...Sunday School", circa 1965 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Religious Articles by P.D. Browne: (1 of 2), 1956-1974 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Religious Articles by P.D. Browne: (2 of 2), 1956-1974 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Non-Religious Articles by P.D. Browne, 1946-1970 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Collected articles, 1963-1971 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Seventh and James Baptist Church: (1 of 2), 1946-1975 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Seventh and James Baptist Church: (2 of 2), 1946-1975 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Sunday School Teaching, circa 1934 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Baylor University Teaching, 1965-1970 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Baylor Historical Society, 1947, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Joint Action Committee, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Masonic: (1 of 2), 1953-1976 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Masonic: (2 of 2), 1953-1976 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Various Organizations, 1938-1980 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Genealogy of P.D. Browne, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Curriculum Course, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Programs, 1945-1967 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Clippings, 1941-1971 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Obituaries, 1950-1981 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Certificates, 1919-1981 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Public Speaking Notes, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Photographs, 1941-1985, undated; 5
    This subseries contains photographs of P.D. Browne, the Fairfield area where he worked for a time, and some general photographs, including one of him purchasing a new car.
    - General, 1954-1985, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - P.D. Browne, 1943-1978 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Fairfield, Texas, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Baylor Materials, 1946-1986; 2
  - Correspondence, 1971-1986; 1
    This subseries contains materials from Browne's extensive career as a teacher and administrator at Baylor University. After teaching in the math and religion departments, Browne served as director of a program for retired professors. He was also active in the Baylor Alumni Association.
    - General, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - General, 1982-1983 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - General, 1984-1986 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Baylor Alumni Association, 1980-1986 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Retirement, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Retirement, 1976-1979 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Literary Productions, circa 1959-1984; 2
    This subseries contains programs from Browne's time at Baylor University, and a copy of his manuscript The Layman and His Church.
    - Programs, 1976-1979 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Programs, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Schedules and Itineraries for Baylor functions, 1980-1982 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - The Layman and His Church (1 of 7), circa 1959-1960 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - The Layman and His Church (2 of 7), circa 1959-1960 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - The Layman and His Church (3 of 7), circa 1959-1960 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - The Layman and His Church (4 of 7), circa 1959-1960 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - The Layman and His Church (5 of 7), circa 1959-1960 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - The Layman and His Church (6 of 7), circa 1959-1960 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - The Layman and His Church (7 of 7), circa 1959-1960 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, 1946-1983; 3
    - General, 1956-1983 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Independence, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Research Interests, 1860 (copy) -1985, undated; 3
  - Correspondence, 1938-1985, undated; 1
    - General, 1938-1961 August (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - General, 1961 October-1962 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - General, 1962 March-October (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - General, 1963 November-1964 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - General, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - General, 1966-1968 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - General, 1969-1972 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - General, 1973-1975 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - General, 1976-1982 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - General, 1983-1985, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - A.M. Maddux, 1861-1862 (copies), undated; 2
    This subseries contains source materials used by Browne for his included essay on Maddux's Company B, 12th Texas Cavalry. The 12th Texas Cavalry, part of Parson's Brigade in the Confederate Trans-Mississippi West, served mostly as scouts and snipers during the Civil War. Browne photocopied muster rolls, correspondence, and requisitions as part of his research; these are included in the subseries.
    - General, 1861-1862 (copies), undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1861-1865 (copies) (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Requesitions, 1862 (copies) (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Essay "Maddux's Company B, 12th Texas Cavalry": (1 of 4), undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Essay "Maddux's Company B, 12th Texas Cavalry": (2 of 4), undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Essay "Maddux's Company B, 12th Texas Cavalry": (3 of 4), undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Essay "Maddux's Company B, 12th Texas Cavalry": (4 of 4), undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - L.D. Bradley, 1860 (copy)-1973, undated; 3
    This subseries contains source materials used by Browne for his included essay on L.D. Bradley's Company B, 2nd Battalion, Waul's Texas Legion. Waul's Texas Legion, part of John C. Pemberton's Vicksburg garrison during the Siege of Vicksburg, was captured and paroled at the end of the campaign. Browne photocopied muster rolls, correspondence, and requisitions as part of his research; these are included in the subseries.
    - General, 1862-1864 (copies), undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1860 (copy)-1973 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Muster Rolls, 1862-1864 (copies) (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Essay "L.D. Bradley's Company": (1 of 7), 1973 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Essay "L.D. Bradley's Company": (2 of 7), 1973 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Essay "L.D. Bradley's Company": (3 of 7), 1973 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Essay "L.D. Bradley's Company": (4 of 7), 1973 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Essay "L.D. Bradley's Company": (5 of 7), 1973 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Essay "L.D. Bradley's Company": (6 of 7), 1973 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Essay "L.D. Bradley's Company": (7 of 7), 1973 (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Notes, 1973, undated (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Photographs, 1963-1972 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Val Verde Battery, 1960-1964; 4
    This subseries contains source materials used by Browne for his included essay on the Val Verde Battery, more formally known as the 12th Texas Light Artillery. The Val Verde Battery, part of Green's Division in the Confederate Trans-Mississippi West, served notably in the Red River Campaign during the Civil War. After the war, the battery buried two of their cannons in and around Fairfield, Texas, to avoid surrendering them to the occupying Federal army. Two of the cannons used by this unit survive today. One is preserved in Fairfield, Texas, on the courthouse lawn, and the other at the Confederate Reunion Grounds State Historic Site, near Mexia, Texas. This interesting story was a major research focus of Browne's, and he produced one of the most accurate histories of the unit, which is preserved in this collection as "Captian T.D. Nettles and the Valverde." Other materials present in this subseries include photocopied muster rolls, correspondence, and requisitions, collected as part of Browne's research.
    - Correspondence, 1963 January-September (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1963 October-December (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1964 January-February (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1964 March-1965 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Printed Materials: (1 of 2), 1960-1961 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Printed Materials: (2 of 2), 1960-1961 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Printed Materials, 1964 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Clippings, 1963-1964 February (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Clippings, 1964 March-1965, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Essay, "Captain T.D. Nettles and the Valverde": (1 of 3), 1963-1964 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Essay, "Captain T.D. Nettles and the Valverde": (2 of 3), 1963-1964 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Essay, "Captain T.D. Nettles and the Valverde": (3 of 3), 1963-1964 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Brochures, 1964, undated (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Notes on T.D. Nettles, undated (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Notes: (1 of 8), undated (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Notes: (2 of 8), undated (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Notes: (3 of 8), undated (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Notes: (4 of 8), undated (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - Notes: (5 of 8), undated (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Notes: (6 of 8), undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Notes: (7 of 8), undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Notes: (8 of 8), undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Photographs, Cannons, 1963 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Photographs, T.D. Nettles, 1963, undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Negatives, 1963 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Freestone County, 1861 (copy)-1978, undated; 5
    This subseries contains source materials used by Browne for several included essays on early Freestone County. Also of note is Brown's interest in post-war Confederate reunions in Freestone County; an essay and related source materials are present on this topic.
    - Muster Rolls, 1861 (copy) (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Essay, General, 1978, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Essay, "Evidences of Culture and Refinement in Freestone County", 1964 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Essay, "Bible Influence in Pioneer Freestone County": (1 of 2), undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Essay, "Bible Influence in Pioneer Freestone County": (2 of 2), undated (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Essay, "Freestone County's Tragic Decade": (1 of 3), 1972 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Essay, "Freestone County's Tragic Decade": (2 of 3), 1972 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Essay, "Freestone County's Tragic Decade": (3 of 3), 1972 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Essay, "Freestone County's Tragic Decade": (1 of 2), undated (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Essay, "Freestone County's Tragic Decade": (2 of 2), undated (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Essay, "The Fairfield Confederate Reunions": (1 of 2), 1973 (Folder 17)
    - Essay, "The Fairfield Confederate Reunions": (2 of 2), 1973 (Folder 18)
    - Brochure, "The Fairfield Confederate Reunions", 1973 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - "Reunion Twenty-Five Years Ago", 1937 (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Essay, "Foolish Fighting", 1926 (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - Essay, "History of Caney Baptist Church", undated (Box 11, Folder 22)
    - Printed Materials, 1970-1972, undated (Box 11, Folder 23)
    - Printed Materials, First Baptist Church, Fairfield, Texas, 1956 (Box 11, Folder 24)
    - Notes, undated (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - Walker's Division, undated; 6
    This subseries contains source materials used by Browne for his included essay "Freestone County Captains in Walker's Division." These apparently included Means' Company H, 28th Texas Cavalry, Waldrom's Company I, 12th Texas Infantry, Peck's Company I, 12th Texas Infantry, and Wilson's Company D, 10th Texas Infantry. Browne photocopied muster rolls, correspondence, and requisitions as part of his research; these are included in the subseries.
    - Essay, "Freestone County Captains in Walker's Division": (1 of 5), undated (Box 11, Folder 26)
    - Essay, "Freestone County Captains in Walker's Division": (2 of 5), undated (Box 11, Folder 27)
    - Essay, "Freestone County Captains in Walker's Division": (3 of 5), undated (Box 11, Folder 28)
    - Essay, "Freestone County Captains in Walker's Division": (4 of 5), undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Essay, "Freestone County Captains in Walker's Division": (5 of 5), undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Means' Company, undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Waldrom's Company, undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Peck's Company, undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Wilson's Company, undated (Box 12, Folder 6)